Guide to the Women's Environment and Development Organization records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Women's Environment and Development Organization (WEDO), undated, 1980-2006 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1998]
  - Subseries I.5: Conferences, Campaigns and Organizations, 1990-2000
    - "Gender Justice: Women's Rights Are Human Rights," 1996 (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - International Development Conference, 1997 January 13-15 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - International Forum on Globalization, 1995 (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - International Women's Day, 1997 (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - International Women's Year--"U.S. Participation in International Women's Year," 1972-1977" Background Paper, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Inter-Parliamentary Union Conference, Canberra, Australia, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Inter-Parliamentarian Symposium.. ., 1989 (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Jewish Women's Coalition, 1996-1997 (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Micro Credit Summit, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Multilateral Agreement on Investment (MAI), undated, 1998 (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - National Commission on Women Ad-Hoc Committee, 1995-1997 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - National Research Council on Women, undated, 1997-1999 (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - National Women's Conference 20th Anniversary
      - Committee and Organizing Group, 1977-1998 (Box 18, Folder 12-13)
      - Meeting, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 1-2)
    - National Women's Conference Committee--Midcourse Corrections and New Beginnings, 1993 (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - National Working Women's Summit, 1997 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Network Women in Development Europe (WIDE), 1996-1997 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Pacific Institute Health Plus Teleconference, 1996 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - S8 Mobilization: The People's Summit, 2000 September 6-8 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - "A Small World After All," 2001 (Box 38, Folder 9)
    - Social Watch, 1995-1997 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - United States Department of Labor, 1992-1997 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - United States National Action Agenda Draft, 1996-1997 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - "Women and Global Action," 1997 March (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - "Weaving a Better Future," 1995-1996 (Box 38, Folder 10)
    - WEDO Primer, 1995 (Box 38, Folder 11)
    - "Women Challenging Globalization," 2002 March 18-20 (Box 38, Folder 12)
    - Women Food Farmers Luncheon, 2000 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - "Women's Action Agenda... ," [199-] (Box 38, Folder 13)
    - Women's International Policy Action Committee, 1991-1998 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Women's Voices: A Joint Project Ms. Foundation for Women/Center for Policy Alternatives, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - World Conference on Breast Cancer, July 13-17, 1997 (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - World Trade Organization (WTO)
      - 1996-1997 (Box 20, Folder 7)
      - 1998, (2 Folders) (Box 20, Folder 8-9)
    - World Women Parliamentarians for Peace, undated, 1987-1988 (Box 20, Folder 10)
- Series II: Women's Foreign Policy Council, 1985-1990
  The Women's Foreign Policy Council series includes a copy of the original Council proposal, some correspondence, materials on two conferences attended by the Council, an environmental fact sheet developed by the Council, and a copy of the 1987 Women's Foreign Policy Council Directory.
  - General, undated, 1988-1991 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Disarmament and Daycare--Soviet-American Women's Summit, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - International Interdisciplinary Congress on Women, 1990 (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - Proposal, 1985-1986 (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - Skaggs Foundation Correspondence and Proposals, 1985-1990 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Women and the Environmental Crisis Fact Sheet, undated (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - Women's Foreign Policy Council Directory, 1987 (Box 21, Folder 7)
- Series III: United Nations, 1972-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1996]
  Series III: United Nations is divided into three subseries. The series focuses largely on WEDO's (and to a smaller extent, Women USA Fund and the Foreign Policy Council's) work with and at the United Nations in developing policy, WEDO attendance at major conferences sponsored by UN offices, and tracking subjects of interest regarding the UN including its reform and operation. In addition, there is extensive documentation on the United Nation's monumental World Women's Conference held in Beijing, China, attended by Abzug, Kelber, and several WEDO members, in 1994.
  - Subseries III.1: Conferences, Campaigns and Organizations, 1979-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1996]
    This subseries documents WEDO's work with various United Nations offices including the Children's Fund (UNICEF), the Commission on Sustainable Development (CSD), the Development Programme (UNDP), General Assembly Special Assemblies (UNGASS), and the Development Fund for Women (UNIFEM) including conference materials, correspondence, reports, and memos generated by the UN, WEDO, and various NGOs. Of note are materials regarding the Earth Summit Agenda 21 held in Rio de Janeiro in 1992, and its follow-up session, Rio +5, as well as follow-up to the International Conference on Population and Development (UNICPD) conference held in Cairo in 1994, and the Beijing Women's Conference (Beijing +5). Some materials and correspondence on the World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the United Nations Decade for Women, held in Nairobi, Kenya in 1985 are also included.
    - General, 1989-2000 (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Children's Fund Non-Government Organization Consultation, 1995 (Box 21, Folder 9)
    - Commission on Sustainable Development, 1995-2000 (Box 21, Folder 10)
    - Conference on Environment and Development, undated, 1992 (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - Convention on the Elimination of All Forms of Discrimination Against Women, 1979-1980, 1993-1997 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Development Fund for Women
      - General, 2000 (Box 22, Folder 4)
      - International Research and Training Institute for the Advancement of Women Merger, 1994 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Development Program, 1996-2000 (Box 22, Folder 5-6)
    - General Assembly Special Session
      - Rio +5, 1997 (Box 22, Folder 7)
      - Rio +5, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      - Beijing +5, 2000 June 5-9 (Box 23, Folder 2-3)
    - Global Policy Forum on United Nations Reform Conference, 1994, 1997 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - International Conference on Population and Development and Implementing Policy After Cairo Forums, 1994-1996 (Box 23, Folder 5-6)
    - International Conference on Population and Development, undated, 1997-1999 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - International Women's Day Forum, 1994 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Non-Governmental Organizations
      - Advisory Committee to the Fund for Population Activities, 1996 (Box 23, Folder 9)
      - Committee on Disarmament, 1996 (Box 23, Folder 10)
      - Task Force Group for a National Women's Organizing Body, 1996 (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - Research Institute for Social Development, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - "United Nations and Civil Society," 1995 October 12 (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - "We the People.. .: The Role of Civil Society in the History and Future of the United Nations" Conference, 1995 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the United Nations Decade for Women, 1985 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - World in Need of Leadership: Tomorrow's United Nations, A Fresh Appraisal, Brian Urquhart and Erskine Childers, 1996 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - World Summit on Sustainable Development (WSSD), 1994 (Box 24, Folder 7)
  - Subseries III.2: World Women's Conference--Beijing, China, 1989-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1996]
    While Subseries III.1 contains some materials on the Beijing Conference and its follow-up, Beijing +5, Subseries III.2 holds the greater majority of correspondence, planning documents, memos, reports, and follow-up materials regarding the UN’s 4th conference on women. This series contains items regarding preparation for the conference, WEDO committee work, Platform for Action formulation and proposed re-writes, addresses and statements, and WEDO's work after the conference in order to promote the implementation of the Platform for Action.
    - General, 1995 (Box 24, Folder 8-10)
    - Addresses and Statements, 1995 (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Before and After, 1995-2000 (Box 25, Folder 3-6)
    - Commission on the Status of Women Preparatory Committee, 1991-1994 (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Credentialing, 1995-1996 (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Davis, Susan--After Beijing Schedule, Invitations and Events, 1995 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Government Commitments and Accountability, 1995, 1999 (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - New York City Report Back Meeting, 1995 October 25 (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Non-Governmental Organization
      - Forum on Women Reception (New York), 1995 March 13 (Box 26, Folder 4)
      - Forum on Women Site Plans, 1995 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Northwest Airlines Transportation Grant, 1994-1995 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Platform for Action, 1994-1995 (Box 26, Folder 7-8)
    - Platform for Action, 1994-1995 (Box 27, Folder 1-3)
    - Preliminary Report Version, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Preparations, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Stanley Foundation Conferences, 1989-1996 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - United Nations Commitments Pledge, 1994-1995 (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Zill, Anne--Correspondence, 1995 (Box 27, Folder 8)
  - Subseries III.3: Subjects, 1972, 1994-2000
    This subseries holds material on specific United Nations-related subjects such as reform and restructuring; the 1994 sexual harassment appeal of Catherine Claxton, a junior UN member who accused asst. Secretary General Luis Maria Gomez of harassment in 1991; UN relations with NGOs and the United States; UN women's history and data; staffing issues; and the election of a woman as Secretary General.
    - History and Data on Women, undated, 1994-1996 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Peacekeeping and Gender (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Reform
      - Finances, 1994-1995 (Box 28, Folder 3)
      - Restructuring Background Material, undated, 1972, 1994-1996 (Box 28, Folder 4)
      - Women and Peace, 1994-1995 (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Sexual Harassment
      - Catherine Claxton Case, 1994 (Box 28, Folder 6-7)
      - Joint Appeals Board, Mrs. Catherine Claxton Appeal, 1994 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - United Nations
      - Non-Governmental Organizations Relations, 1994-2000 (Box 29, Folder 2)
      - United States Relations, 1995-1996 (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Women and the United Nations
      - Candidates for the Secretary-General, 1996 June (Box 29, Folder 4)
      - Secretariat, 1994-1995 (Box 29, Folder 5)
      - Staffing Issues, 1990s (Box 29, Folder 6)
- Series IV: Abzug, Bella, 1984-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1992-1998]
  The WEDO records contained files pertaining directly to Bella Abzug throughout the collection. These materials were pulled together in order to form a comprehensive series of documentation related to Abzug, particularly her death in 1998 including condolence correspondence and Abzug anecdotes (sent to WEDO and Kelber), memorial service arrangements and the establishment of a memorial fund and leadership award in her name. Articles and speeches written by Abzug herself or by Kelber for Abzug, were placed in this series. Also included is a transcript of the 1999 Lifetime Television documentary on Abzug entitled, Intimate Portraits--Bella Abzug and the unpublished manuscript and research of a children's book (1984) on Abzug written by Beatrice Siegel.
  - Abzug Leadership Awards, 1998-2000 (Box 29, Folder 1-2)
  - Abzug Firing--Articles and Clippings, 1979 (Box 39, Folder 1)
  - Abzug Firing--Letters, 1979 (Box 39, Folder 2)
  - Articles About Abzug, 1992-1998 (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Articles and Speeches (Written by Bella Abzug), 1993-1994 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Articles and Speeches (Written by Mim Kelber), 1989-1996 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Beijing Conference Opening Ceremony Speech, 1994 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - "Bella the Ball," 1991 (Box 39, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Information, undated, 1998 (Box 39, Folder 4)
  - Breast Cancer Climb, 1995 (Box 39, Folder 5)
  - Condolences, 1998 (Box 39, Folder 6)
  - Condolences, 1998 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Empowerment of Jewish Women Speech, 1988 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Funeral and Memorials, 1998 (Box 39, Folder 7)
  - Intimate Portraits: Bella Abzug (Transcripts), 1989 (Box 30, Folder 7-8)
  - Memorial Fund, Bella Abzug
    - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Memorial Fund--Kelber File, 1998, 2000 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Memorial Service
    - Anecdote Correspondence, undated, 1998 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Speeches, 1998 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Photographs and Slides, undated, 1984 circa 1994 (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Press After Abzug's Passing, 1998 (Box 39, Folder 8)
  - Printed Matter, undated, 1998 (Box 31, Folder 4)
  - Siegel, Beatrice--Children's Book Research and Typescript, 1984 (Box 31, Folder 5)
  - Woman of the Year Award--Ms. Magazine, 1998 January-February (Box 31, Folder 6)
- Series V: Publications and Printed Matter, 1974-2000 [Bulk Dates: 1994-1998]
  The collection contained a variety of pamphlets and brochures, newsletters, journals, magazines and newspaper clippings produced both by WEDO and other organizations. The great majority of these materials have been pulled together in Series V, which is divided into three subseries: V.1: WEDO, Women USA Fund, Inc. and the Women's Foreign Policy Council; V.2: Other organizations by subject and V.3: Oversized Printed Matter. Some printed materials were kept in their original locations. The materials contained here were either filed on their own accord or sprinkled throughout the collection. They are filed together for easier retrieval and organization.
  - Subseries V.1: Women's Environment and Development Organization, Women's USA Fund, Women's Foreign Policy Council and Mim Kelber, 1987-2002 [Bulk Dates: 1996-1994]
    This subseries contains many of the materials produced by WEDO, Women's USA Fund, Inc., or the Foreign Policy Council. The subseries includes WEDO reports on the Beijing Conference, breast cancer, the WEDO News and Views newsletter (1998-2002, incomplete) and Primer publication, a guide to early online activism, pamphlets and brochures from WEDO and the World Women's Conference for a Healthy Planet. The Women's Foreign Policy Council Declaration of Independence and Pledge of Allegiance to the Family of Earth are located in this subseries, while the Council's Women's Foreign Policy Council Directory is located in Series II. Also included in this subseries is a copy of the only novel published by Mim Kelber, entitled A Pride of Women.
    - "Building on Beijing: United States NGOs Shape a Women's National Agenda," 1997 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Environmental Links to Breast Cancer Handbook, 1996 (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - "First Steps: What Has Happened Since Beijing?, 1996 March 8 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - "Keeping the Promises...A WEDO Workshop Report," 1996 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - News and Views
      - 1988-1995 (Box 31, Folder 12)
      - 1996-2002 (Box 31, Folder 13)
    - Pamphlets and Brochures, undated, 1987, 1991 (Box 31, Folder 14)
    - Primer, undated, 1999 (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - "Promise Kept, Promise Broken?," 1996-1997 (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - "Women Engaging the UN Online," 1994 (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Women's Foreign Policy Council Declaration of Interdependence and Pledge of Allegiance to the Family of Earth, undated (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - "Women Making a Difference...," 1992 (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - World Women's Congress for a Healthy Planet, 1991 (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Subseries V.2: Other Organizations, 1974-2000
    Subseries V.2 contain magazines, journals, newsletters, reports, articles, clippings and papers produced by other organizations and arranged by subject of publication in alphabetical order. Subjects center on women's issues involving the environment, poverty, reproduction and population, the United Nations, the United States and women refugees, violence against women, human rights, and politics.
    - General, 1995-1996 (Box 32, Folder 7-8)
    - Book Excerpts, Articles, and Papers, undated, 1974, 1989-1996 (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - Donor Countries and Organizations, 1995 (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Education and Poverty, undated, 1994-1997 (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Environmental and Globalization Issues, undated, 1989-1999 (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - European Women Status Report, 1995 (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Feminism and Activism, 1991-1997 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Reproduction and Population, 1995 (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - Symposium and Conference Brochures, 1990s (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - United Nations and Non-Governmental Organizations, 1988-1997 (Box 34, Folder f-1-2)
    - United States and Women Refugees Report, 1997 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Violence Against Women Discussion Paper, 1995 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - War and Disarmament, undated, 1997-1998 (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - "Women and the United Nations" (Roosevelt Institute), 1995 (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - Women Human Rights Reports, 1988, 1993, 1998 (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Women and Politics, undated, 1992-1997 (Box 34, Folder 8-9)
    - Women and Politics, undated, 1992-1997 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Women's Vote and Women's Issues Chronological Clippings
      - 1988 (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - 1989 (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - 1990 (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - 1991 (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - 1992 (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - 1993 (Box 35, Folder 7)
      - 1994 (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - Post-Election, 1994 (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - 1995 (Box 35, Folder 10)
      - 1996 (Box 35, Folder 11)
      - 1997 (Box 35, Folder 12)
      - 1998 (Box 35, Folder 13)
      - 1999 (Box 35, Folder 14)
      - 2000 (Box 35, Folder 15)
    - General, 1995-2000 (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Eco, Action for a Common Future (Bergen Conference), 1990 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Earth Times, 1994-1996 (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - ICPD +5 Watch, 1999 July 2 (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - Terra Viva, 1997, 2000 (Box 36, Folder 5)
  - Subseries V.3: Oversized Printed Matter, 1977-1997.
    Four oversized posters have been removed from the general records and placed in oversized storage. The posters include a copy of the Contract with Women of the USA New York Times advertisement, a 1977 copy of the National Women's Conference poster, a 75th Anniversary of Women's Suffrage poster produced by the Center for Policy Alternatives, and a poster from a women's conference held in Modena, Italy in 1997.
    - "American Women on the Move" (Poster), 1977 (Box 14-O-2)
    - Contract with Women of the USA--New York Times Advertisement, 1996 (Box 14-O-2)
    - "State of the States for Women and Politics" (Poster), 1995 (Box 14-O-2)
    - Sviluppo Umano Sostenibile: Una Prospettiva Di Genere (Poster), 1997 (Box 14-O-2)
- Series VI: Audio Visual Material, 1991-2005
  Audio visual materials include VHS tapes and DVDs of WEDO public relations reels, Bella Abzug memorials, and interviews conducted by Lee Grant of Mim Kelber for Intimate Portraits-- Bella Abzug. Audio materials include two microcassettes of interviews conducted by Libby Bassett in 2000 for a history of WEDO. Rounding out this series are speeches by Harry Kelber, the husband of Mim Kelber and noted AFL-CIO leader, produced by the AFL-CIO in honor of his union leadership and service.
  - "An Evening with Harry Kelber: 70 Years in the Labor Movement," 2006 (DVD) (Box 37)
  - "Bella at the Ball," 1991 May (VHS) (Box 37)
  - "Bella's Last Decade" United Nations Memorial Service, 1998 April 24 (VHS) (Box 37)
  - "Earthspinners," Rough Cut Dub Fundraising, 1992 October 27 (VHS) (Box 37)
  - "Giving Women An Equal Say!," undated (VHS) (Box 37)
  - History Interviews Microcassettes, circa 2000 (2) (Box 37)
  - Intimate Portrait: Bella Abzug, Lee Grant Interviews Mim Kelber, 1998 April (DVD) (Box 37)